Suryansh Jalan

Co Founder at Dipper

Summary

"Be the Change you want to see." This is a statement that has always appealed greatly to me. Pursuing my various interests has allowed me to wear several different caps- Researcher, Marketer, Manager, Writer, Engineer and Strategist. From working in a rural village with the Government of India, to a struggling start-up, to a Manufacturing Factory at a Forbes 20 most admired company. I have always thrown myself at opportunities in areas I'm passionate about. As a result I find it easy to be a part of multi-disciplinary projects and to navigate tough challenges. I love making new professional acquaintances. Touch base if you want to discuss ideas, technology, entrepreneurship or football. Specialties: Industrial Engineering, 6 Sigma, Kanban, Logistics, Social Media, Brand Strategy and Development

Experience

Co Founder at Dipper

June 2015 - Present (8 months)

85% of India's 3 million Commercial Vehicles belong to small fleet owners (less than 10 trucks) making the industry highly fragmented and allowing middlemen to eat up over 25% of trucker's profits just for load matching. Dipper is an online platform that connects load providers (GTA) with load seekers (Truck Owners)- without commissions! In a country where logistics cost are 2-3 times the international benchmark, we leverage technology and pass the benefits and transparency onto you (the load owner/movers) so that you can, 'Drive your own freight!' Know more at www.UseDipper.com

Logistics Engineer 3 at Caterpillar Inc.

July 2014 - April 2015 (10 months)

Supply Chain Management- Procurement, CIPL (January'15- April'15) - Material Requirement Controller for 50+ International Suppliers - Planned, Scheduled material requirement and movements for 450+ parts with a resultant Part Availability of 100% - Saved excess stock scrap worth \$10,000+ - Awarded 6 Sigma Green Belt certification for directly creating value of over \$1,000,000 through various projects. - Primary Licensee and Lead Organizer, TEDxCaterpillarTiruvallur Logistics Planning and Engineering, IMOD and HEX (July'14- January'15) - Investigated, mitigated part unavailability as the Point of Use Availability governor.

- Managed 70+ vehicles as the Material Handling Equipment (MHE) coordinator. - Created storage locations and fixtures for material movement as Planning Engineer for Axle Plant and HEX

Logistics Analyst 2 at Caterpillar Inc.

July 2013 - July 2014 (1 year 1 month)

April-July'14: Logistics Planning Engineer, Building Construction Products (BCP-India) - Worked to introduce Paint Before Assembly (PBA) for all products - Performed a study of ~60% of the Back-Hoe Loader parts to reduce quality and rework issues - Developed special pallets (inhouse) for parts and MHE fork storage. July'13-April'14: Section Manager, Axle Machine Shop Logistics- IMOD - Oversaw everyday logistics of the manufacturing unit, supervising 10+individuals. - Designed and implemented a study to reduce Throughput Time by 68% and Work In Progress by 40%, by ascertaining total time of machining process, evaluating and mitigating bottlenecks and Non-Value added activities (NVAs) - Reduced Inventory costs by 62% and Part Unavailability to 0% by creating a parts staging area based on Kanban process.

Head and Chief Editor at Paisa Inc.

October 2012 - July 2013 (10 months)

Paisa Inc. is E-Cell, NIT-T's monthly magazine that deals with all things entrepreneurial. To know more, visit www.facebook.com/PaisaInc - Setting up the structure and introducing the magazine - Supervising the content and design - Strategic Consulting- Planning long and short term goals - Social Media Marketing and Brand Development to grow the magazine

International Marketing Director at pickabit

October 2011 - October 2012 (1 year 1 month)

pickabit is a worldwide community of members who buy and sell items, services, and skills without the interest rates or other arbitrary fees charged by banks, credit cards, or conventional financial methods. - Assisted in the launching of the startup. - Social Media Marketing - Brand Development - Developed and implemented brand strategy on short term and long term goals - Oversaw the running of Marketing team with 10+ individuals from across the world. - Created and implemented several projects for growth in reach and website traffic.

Education

National Institute of Technology Tiruchirappalli

B. Tech, Production Engineering, 2009 - 2013

Grade: First Class with Distinction

Activities and Societies: Entrepreneurship Cell, Football Team, Marketing Team- Pragyan'12 Publicity team-Pragyan'11, Marketing Team- Festember, Rotaract Club of NIT-T.

Ruparel College, Mumbai

HSC, Science, 2007 - 2009

Campion School, Mumbai

ICSE, 1997 - 2007

Activities and Societies: Member of Student Council, Football Team, Cricket Team, Basketball Team

Languages

English

(Native or bilingual proficiency)

Hindi

(Native or bilingual proficiency)

(Limited working proficiency)
(Limited working proficiency)

Honors and Awards

6 Sigma Green Belt (Certified)

Caterpillar University

April 2015

To certify that Suryansh is trained in the 6 Sigma recipes and has implemented the methodology to directly create value of over \$1,000,000 through various projects he has participated and led.

Skills & Expertise

Social Media

Social Media Marketing

Market Research

Customer Service

Entrepreneurship

Social Networking

Marketing Strategy

Marketing

Microsoft Excel

Recruiting

Research

Business Development

Analysis

Start-ups

Team Management

Six Sigma

Teamwork

Manufacturing

Project Planning

Strategy

Projects

Study on Bottleneck Analysis and Facility Layout on a shop-floor using FlexSim Software

January 2013 to Present

Members: Suryansh J., Prannay Mitra, Sakshi Soni

The objective of the project was to utilize FlexSim software in order to boost the throughput of a piperiser manufacturing shop at BHEL. This was done through bottleneck mitigation and achieving optimum facility layout on the simulated model. Guide: Dr. Prasanna Venkatesan Result: 35% increase in output upon implementation. Line balanced and WIP,Inventory reduced.

A Tribology study on the effect of Surface Texture and Lubricants on friction using a ball-on- plate inclined scratch tester.

May 2011 to July 2011

Members:Suryansh J., Monish Banerjee

Summer Research Project at IISc, Bangalore under the guidance of Dr. Satish V. Kailas. The objective of the project was to test the effect of different surfaces (texture, finish, etc) and lubricants(oils and soaps) under various conditions of loading using a ball-on-plate sliding tester and hence calculate the coefficient of friction between the materials. The results were used to determine variance of friction with above properties and hence achieve optimum conditions.

Test Scores

GMAT

December 2012 Score:740

Percentile: 98%

Organizations

CatMiners Toastmasters Club

Vice President- Education June 2014 to April 2015

Young Professionals of Caterpillar

Professional Development- Core Team

August 2013 to April 2015

TEDx Caterpillar Tiruvallur

Primary Licensee and Lead Organizer

August 2014 to August 2015

Brought the concept of TEDx to the company and organized the first ever Internal TEDx event at Caterpillar world-wide.

Volunteer Experience

Volunteer at Vatsalya Foundation- Mumbai

July 2007 - Present (8 years 7 months)

President at Interact Club of Campion School

July 2007 - Present (8 years 7 months)

With the aim of shaping our immediate environment we organised several education camps where children from our school would teach elementary Math and English to those from the neighboring schools for the underprivileged. Several newspaper drives and other eco-friendly rallies were held to raise money for clothes and shelter. Social Awareness camps were organised to spread the message.

Suryansh Jalan

Co Founder at Dipper



10 people have recommended Suryansh

"First thing to mention about Suryansh is his ability to challenge the fundamentals. He is not ready to get convinced to accept a process just because it was performed that way. He had been valuable resource for us, providing out of the box ideas and approaching the tasks in a structured way. I wish him all success in all his future atempts."

— Senthil Kumar K., Six Sigma Black Belt, Caterpillar Inc., managed Suryansh indirectly at Caterpillar Inc.

"I have known Suryansh as a service provider in the logistics department, as the Vice President Education of the Caterpillar Toastmasters Club and as a reliable friend. When it comes to understanding, following and enforcing a set of rules/protocol, I haven't seen anyone better. He is a leader driven by strong principles. He takes up every assignment that comes his way very seriously and does full justice to it. A the VPE of the Toastmasters club, he has led the educational goals of the 40 member team diligently; many new members have benefited from his close mentor-ship. He has stepped into the shoe of the Club President and led the club whenever it was needed. Strong communication and organisational skills are his biggest strengths. I wish him the very best for his future endeavors."

— **Viswanath A.**, *Quality Supervisor, Customer Quality (QA&R), Caterpillar Inc.*, worked with Suryansh at Caterpillar Inc.

"From my time working with Suryansh, I can conclude that he is an exceptionally capable professional who does not refrain from taking on new challenges no matter how daunting it may seem. Another point of note that I have observed during our time at Caterpillar, is that he is always looking for ways to improve or if necessary rehaul existing processes for a better outcome. These traits shall no doubt prove valuable assets in his future endeavours "

— **Mukund Varma A.**, *Section Manager III, Caterpillar Inc.*, worked directly with Suryansh at Caterpillar Inc.

"Suryansh is a manager with initiatives. He has the zeal to do something out of the box and always come up with ideas for the same. He is very focused on the work at hand, and has the determination to see his work through and overcome any obstacle in his way. He strives to keep his team happy and at the same time focused on the goals. Best wishes for his future endeavors."

— Neeraj S., was with another company when working with Suryansh at Paisa Inc.

"Suryansh is a pro-active and objective-oriented manager. He is very sincere in his efforts as a co-worker. He is skillful and efficient in managing a team and planning activities for the team. I have learnt a lot for him while working at Paisa Inc. He constantly strives for excellence and believes in making a difference. I wish him all the best in his future endeavours."

— **Siddharth V.**, reported to Suryansh at Paisa Inc.

"Suryansh is a detail-oriented manager. He makes sure to follow up on every task and see it through to completion. He is a great team player and ensures that everyone participates with enthusiasm. He is dedicated to his role and the tasks at hand and will work to ensure that deadlines are met,"

— Riya K., reported to Suryansh at pickabit

"Suryansh is adaptable, able to deal with change and invariably achieves his objectives. He is very positive, enthusiastic and not least extremely persistent, never giving up, but always eager to pursue the goal. He is a true team-player, always eager to help, with a very positive and open attitude to whatever challenges may meet his eye. I wish Suryansh all the best in the future."

— Rita G., worked directly with Suryansh at pickabit

"I have been knowing Suyansh since almost six years, and the only thing that comes to my mind about him is his efficiency. He has always proved himself as Jack of all trades, be it academics or extra-curricular, he always manages to stay ahead of the crowd."

— **Pratik D.**, studied with Suryansh at National Institute of Technology Tiruchirappalli

"Suryansh is full of bright ideas of and an expert in finding ways to implement it. He has been the Editor of Paisa Inc and has produced wonderful piece of work. He never fails to explore the possibilities and trying out new things."

— Akash Arun, studied with Suryansh at National Institute of Technology Tiruchirappalli

"I have worked with Suryansh in project during our final year of B.tech and have spent a lot of time with him analyzing and solving academic problems. I ought to say i haven't seen him getting struck without any alternate option for the work around. If there are many ways to deal with a situation, he knows the shortest yet most productive way to work out. He is a great team-player and very result oriented person. He is very keen to get solutions, possess broad minded thinking. He never misses out minute details even though if he is dealing with major risky situations. I will recommend him as every team needs a motivator, a person who can not only solve his issues easily but help others to get out of their troubles too, so that all can progress together

and move ahead as team. Having him in a team will ensure that there will always be a work around very soon, if there is any blocking issue in project."

— Pranay Karodi, studied with Suryansh at National Institute of Technology Tiruchirappalli

Contact Suryansh on LinkedIn